FieldId	HES_FieldName	FieldName	Description	Class	LengthFormat	Availability	DataCleaning	IsCategorical
1592	Admission date check flag	adm_cfl	Codes in this field indicate whether the patient's admission date is valid.	Admissions	1n	All years	Not applicable (derived by rule 35)	
1593	Date of admission	admidate	This field contains the date the patient was admitted to hospital at the start of a hospital spell. 
Admidate is recorded on all episodes within a spell.	Admissions	dd/mm/yyyy (Date)	All years	Rule 35	
1594	Date of decision to admit	elecdate	This field contains the date on which a consultant, or another member of the clinical staff, 
decided to admit the patient to a hospital. 
The patient may or may not be admitted immediately. The time between elecdate and 
admidate (admission date) is known as the waiting time.	Admissions	dd/mm/yyyy (Date)	All years	Rules 40 and 45	
1595	Date of decision to admit check flag	elec_cfl	Codes in this field indicate whether the decision to admit date is valid.	Admissions	1n	All years	Not applicable: derived by Rules 40 and 45	
1596	First regular day or night admission	firstreg	This field indicates whether the episode falls within a sequence of regular day and night 
admissions and, if so, whether it is the first or subsequent episode within the sequence.	Admissions	1n	From 2002-03	None	
1597	Method of admission	admimeth	This field contains a code which identifies how the patient was admitted to hospital. Admimeth 
is recorded on the first and also all subsequent episodes within the spell (ie where the spell is 
made up of more than one episode).	Admissions	2n	All years	Rules 65, 70 and 320	
1598	Source of admission	admisorc	This field contains a code which identifies where the patient was immediately prior to 
admission. 
Most patients are admitted from home, but there are some significant exceptions. In 
particular, this field differentiates between patients admitted from home and patients 
transferred from another hospital provider or institution.	Admissions	2n	All years	Rule 80	
1599	Waiting time	elecdur	This derived field contains the difference in days between the date on which it was decided to 
admit the patient (elecdate) and the actual admission date (admidate). 
Elecdur is only applicable where an elective admission (ie the admission method is 11, 12 or 
13) was scheduled and took place.	Admissions	4n		Not applicable (derived by rule 270)	
1600	ACP sequence number	acpseq	Augmented care period sequence number.	Augmented/critical care period	1n	From 1 October 1997 to 31 March 2006	None	
1601	Augmented care location	acploc	This field gives the location of a patient during a period of augmented care.	Augmented/critical care period	2n	From 1 October 1997 to 31 March 2006	Rules 950 and 960	
1602	Augmented care period disposal	acpdisp	This field gives the destination of a discharged patient after a period of augmented care. 
Compare this field with disdest (destination on discharge from a hospital episode).	Augmented/critical care period	2n	From 1 October 1997 to 31 March 2006	Rules 920 and 930	
1603	Augmented care period end date	acpend	This field gives the end date of a period of augmented care (a null entry indicates that this 
data is not applicable).	Augmented/critical care period	dd/mm/yyyy (Date)	From 1 October 1997 to 31 March 2006	Rule 940	
1604	Augmented care period local ID	acplcid	There are no nationally agreed values for this item. This field contains sensitive data. Access 
to it requires the approval of the Database Monitoring Sub-Group (DMSG).	Augmented/critical care period	8an	From 2002-03 to 31 March 2006	None	
1605	Augmented care period number	acpn	This field contains a number representing the order of an episode within a sequence of 
episodes that make up a period of augmented care.	Augmented/critical care period	2n	From 1 October 1997 to 31 March 2006	Rule 970	
1606	Augmented care period outcome indicator	acpout	This field identifies whether a patient survived. For deaths it indicates whether organs were 
donated. 
Organs are defined as whole organs such as heart, lung, liver, kidney and pancreas. The 
value 03 does not include parts of organs such as corneas, heart valves, etc.	Augmented/critical care period	2n	From 1 October 1997 to 31 March 2006	Rule 980 and Rule 990	
1607	Augmented care period planned indicator	acpplan	This field indicates whether any part of the ACP was planned in advance of admission to the 
ACP location.	Augmented/critical care period	1n	From 1 October 1997 to 31 March 2006	Rule 1000	
1608	Augmented care period source	acpsour	This field defines where the patient was immediately before the period of augmented care. 
Compare this field with admisorc (source of patient for a hospital episode).	Augmented/critical care period	2n	From 1 October 1997 to 31 March 2006	Rule 900 and Rule 910	
1609	Augmented care period speciality function code	acpspef	This field contains the code for the main specialty of the consultant clinically managing the 
period of augmented care. 
This consultant is not necessarily the same as the one responsible for the hospital episode. 
Where a patient is cared for by a team of specialists within an Intensive Care rota, this field 
contains the specialty of the team's clinical director. 
Where there are several specialties involved but none is considered responsible, this field 
contains the specialty of the consultant admitting the patient to the period of augmented care. 
If no specific consultant or team can be identified as organising the care associated with the 
ACP, then this should be the same as for the related consultant episode.	Augmented/critical care period	3n	From 1 October 1997 to 31 March 2006	Rule 1010	
1610	Augmented care period start date	acpstar	This field states the start date of a period of augmented care.	Augmented/critical care period	dd/mm/yyyy = Date	From 1 October 1997 to 31 March 2006	Rule 1020	
1611	High-dependency care level	depdays	This field contains the number of days of high dependency care in a period of augmented 
care.	Augmented/critical care period	4n	From 1 October 1997 to 31 March 2006	Rule 1030	
1612	Intensive care level days	intdays	This field contains the number of days of intensive care in a period of augmented care.	Augmented/critical care period	4n	From 1 October 1997 to 31 March 2006	Rule 1040	
1613	Number of augmented care periods within episode	numacp	This derived field gives the number of augmented care periods (ACPs) within episode.	Augmented/critical care period	2n	From 1 October 1997 to 31 March 2006	Not applicable (derived by rule 1060)	
1614	Number of organ systems supported	orgsup	This field contains the number of organ support systems used (up to five) during a period of 
augmented care.	Augmented/critical care period	2n	From 1 October 1997 to 31 March 2006	Rule 1050	
1615	Date of operation	opdte_nn	This field contains the dates for operations recorded in the operation codes (oper_nn) field. 
There is room for twenty-four dates (twelve prior to April 2002).	Clinical	dd/mm/yyyy (Date)		Rules 480, 485, 610 and 620	
1616	All diagnosis codes	diag_nn	There are twenty fields (fourteen before April 2007 and seven before April 2002), diag_01 to 
diag_20, which contain information about a patient's illness or condition. 
The field diag_01 contains the primary diagnosis. The other fields contain 
secondary/subsidiary diagnoses. The codes are defined in the International Statistical 
Classification of Diseases, Injuries and Causes of Death. 
HES records currently use the tenth revision (ICD-10). Prior to April 1995, the ninth revision 
was used (ICD-9). Diagnosis codes start with a letter and are followed by two or three digits. 
The third digit identifies variations on a main diagnosis code containing two digits. 
The third digit is preceded by a full stop in ICD-10, but this is not stored in the field.	Clinical	6an		Rules 460, 470, 490, 500, 510, 530, 630, 640, 840 and 850	
1617	Cause code - 4 characters	cause4dg	This item is a copy of the initial 4 characters of the first diagnosis code that represents an 
external cause, eg accidents or poisoning.	Clinical	4an		Rules 460, 470, 510 and 530 (then derived by rule 580)	
1618	Cause code - 3 characters	cause3	This item is a copy of the initial 3 characters of the first diagnosis code that represents an 
external cause, eg accidents or poisoning.	Clinical	3an		Rules 460, 470, 510 and 530 (then derived by rule 580)	
1619	Cause code	cause	External cause of injury or poisoning. This item is a copy of the first diagnosis code that 
represents an external cause.	Clinical	6an		Rules 460, 470, 510 and 530 (then derived by rule 580)	
1620	Intended management	intmanig	This field contains a code that defines what was planned to happen. The patient classification 
(classpat) defines what actually happened.	Clinical	1n	From 1997-98	Rule 120	
1621	Main operative procedure - 3 characters	oper3	This provides the first three characters of the main operation (oper_1).	Clinical	3an, - or &		Not applicable (this item is derived from a cleaned field)	
1622	Main specialty	mainspef	This field contains a code that defines the specialty under which the consultant is contracted. 
It can be compared with tretspef, the specialty under which the consultant worked.	Clinical	3n or &		Rule 90 and Rule 350	
1623	All operative procedure codes	oper_nn	There are twenty-four fields (twelve before April 2007 and four prior to April 2002), oper_01 to 
oper_24, which contain information about a patient's operations. 
The field oper_01 contains the main (ie most resource intensive) procedure. The other fields 
contain secondary procedures. 
The codes are defined in the Tabular List of the Classification of Surgical Operations and 
Procedures. The current version is OPCS4. Procedure codes start with a letter and are 
followed by two or three digits. 
The third digit identifies variations on a main procedure code containing two digits. The third 
digit is preceded by a full stop in OPCS4, but this is not stored in the field. A single operation 
may contain more than one procedure.	Clinical	4an, - or &		Rules 450, 540, 550, 560, 610 and 620	
1624	Operation status code	operstat	Status of operation.	Clinical	1n	From 2002-03	None	
1625	Patient classification	classpat	This field identifies day cases, ordinary admissions, regular day and regular night attenders, 
and the special case of mothers and babies using only delivery facilities. 
Data about regular day and regular night attenders are not available for analysis prior to 
2002-03. Since the introduction of the NHS wide clearing service in April 1996, this field has 
been derived from related items in the Commissioning Data Set (eg intended management).	Clinical	1n		Not applicable (derived by rule 260)	
1626	Post-operative duration	posopdur	This derived field contains the difference in days between the date of the main operation 
(opdte_01) and the date the episode ended (epiend).	Clinical	3n		Not applicable (derived by rule 1070)	
1627	Pre-operative duration	preopdur	This derived field contains the difference in days between the date the episode started 
(epistart) and the date of the main operation (opdte_01).	Clinical	3n		Not applicable (derived by rule 1075)	
1628	Primary diagnosis - 4 characters	diag4	This provides the first four characters of the primary diagnosis (diag_01).	Clinical	4an		Not applicable (derived from a cleaned field)	
1629	Primary diagnosis - 3 characters	diag3	This provides the first three characters of the primary diagnosis (diag_01).	Clinical	3an		Not applicable (derived from a cleaned field)	
1630	Primary diagnosis chapter	chapter	This provides the chapter of the primary diagnosis (diag_01).	Clinical	4an			
1631	Treatment specialty	tretspef	This field contains a code that defines the specialty in which the consultant was working 
during the period of care. It can be compared with mainspef, the specialty under which the 
consultant is contracted. 
Prior to 1 April 1996, this data item contained the code for the sub-specialty (subspef). From 
April 2004 a new list of treatment specialities was introduced (see below). 
The new list describes the specialised service within which the patient was treated.	Clinical	3n or &		Rule 100	
1632	Ambulatory Care Sensitive Condition Flag	Acscflag	Ambulatory Care Sensitive Condition flag is derived for finished APC episodes where the 
admission method is 'emergency'. The flag indicates whether the episode contains a 
diagnosis which is ambulatory care sensitive	Diagnosis	1n	2007-2008 onwards	Derived by rule 509	
1633	Principal alcohol related diagnosis	Alcdiag	Indicates the diagnosis code with the highest alcohol attributable fraction. Where this applies 
to more than one code, the code that appears earliest in the sequence of diagnosis fields is 
used. Where no alcohol attributable diagnosis is present this field will be null. Please refer to 
the supplementary table, 'Refreshed Indicator Conditions and Fractions', on the Data 
Dictionaries page of HESonline for more information 
[http://www.hesonline.nhs.uk/Ease/servlet/ContentServer?siteID=1937&categoryID=289].	Diagnosis	6an	2002-2003 onwards	Derived by rule 1230	
1634	Principal alcohol related fraction	Alcfrac	Indicates the highest alcohol attributable fraction within the episode based on the principal 
alcohol related diagnosis. Please refer to the supplementary table, 'Refreshed Indicator 
Conditions and Fractions', on the Data Dictionaries page of HESonline for more information 
[http://www.hesonline.nhs.uk/Ease/servlet/ContentServer?siteID=1937&categoryID=289].	Diagnosis	n.nn	2002-2003 onwards	Derived by rule 1230	
1635	Date of discharge	disdate	This field contains the date on which the patient was discharged from hospital. 
It is only present in the record for the last episode of a spell.	Discharges	dd/mm/yyyy (Date)	All years	Rules 205, 210, 220 and 223	
1636	Destination on discharge	disdest	This field contains a code which identifies where the patient was due to go on leaving 
hospital. In most cases they return home. 
For many patients discharge destination is the same as source of admission (admisorc).	Discharges	2n		Rules 205, 210, 220 and 223	
1637	Discharge date check flag	dis_cfl	Codes in this field indicate whether the discharge date (disdate) is valid.	Discharges	1n		Not applicable (derived by rules 205, 210, 220 and 223)	
1638	Discharge ready date	disreadydate	The date that a patient was medically ready for discharge from a hospital bed, but couldn't be 
discharged, therefore qualifying for delayed discharge payments.	Discharges	dd/mm/yyyy (Date)	2007-08, Quarter 3 onwards	Data not cleaned	
1639	Method of discharge	dismeth	This field contains a code which defines the circumstances under which a patient left hospital. 
For the majority of patients this is when they are discharged by the consultant. 
This field is only completed for the last episode in a spell.	Discharges	1n		Rules 205, 210, 220, 223 and 320	
1640	Bed days within the year	bedyear	This derived field provides the duration of an episode in days within the HES data year. It is 
derived from epistart (episode start date) and epiend (episode end date). 
For episodes that both start and finish in the data year, bedyear has the same value as epidur 
(episode duration). If the episode is unfinished, bedyear is calculated from epistart and the 
end of the data year. 
If epistart is before the beginning of the data year, bedyear is calculated from the start of the 
data year and epiend. If the record type is other maternity events (episode type 5 or 6), 
bedyear is null.	Episodes and spells	3n	All years	Not applicable (derived by rule 240)	
1641	Beginning of spell	spelbgin	This derived field contains a code that defines whether the episode is the first of a spell and 
whether the spell started in the current or previous year. Other maternity events are excluded.	Episodes and spells	1n		Not applicable (derived by rule 1170)	
1642	Date episode ended	epiend	This field contains the date on which a patient left the care of a particular consultant, for one 
of the following reasons: 
Discharged from hospital (includes transfers) or moved to the care of another consultant. 
A null entry either indicates that the episode was unfinished at the end of the data year, or the 
date was unknown.	Episodes and spells	dd/mm/yyyy (Date)		Rules 190, 200 and 203	
1643	Date episode started	epistart	This field contains the date on which a patient was under the care of a particular consultant. If 
a patient has more than one episode in a spell, for each new episode there is a new value of 
epistart. 
However, the admission date which is copied to each new episode in a spell will remain 
unchanged and will be equal to the episode start date of the first episode in hospital.	Episodes and spells	dd/mm/yyyy (Date)		Rule 30	
1644	Duration of spell	speldur	This derived field contains the difference in days between the admission date (admidate) and 
the discharge date (epiend) provided the discharge method (dismeth) confirms that the spell 
has finished. 
If the episode has not finished it is calculated from the end of the year and admidate.	Episodes and spells	5n		Not applicable (derived by rule 1180)	
1645	End of spell	spelend	This field contains a code which defines whether the episode is the last of a spell. 
It is set for finished episodes (episode status - epistat - is 3) for general, delivery or birth 
episodes (episode type - epitype - is 1, 2 or 3) provided the discharge method (dismeth) 
confirms that the spell has finished.	Episodes and spells	1a		Not applicable (derived by rule 1190)	
1646	Episode duration	epidur	This field contains the difference in days between the episode start date (epistart) and the 
episode end date (epiend). 
If the episode is unfinished epidur is set as null.	Episodes and spells	5n		Not applicable (derived by rule 250)	
1647	Episode end date check flag	epie_cfl	This field validates the episode end date (epiend).	Episodes and spells	1n		Not applicable	
1648	Episode order	epiorder	This field contains the number of the episode within the current spell. All spells start with an 
episode where epiorder is 01. 
Many spells finish with this episode, but if the patient moves to the care of another consultant, 
a new episode begins. Episode numbers increase by 1 for each new episode until the patient 
is discharged (this includes transfers to another NHS trust or primary care trust - ie the first 
episode in the new trust will have epiorder 01). 
If the same patient returns for a different spell in hospital, epiorder is again set to 01. 
Admissions are calculated by counting the number of times epiorder is 01. When studying 
long term care, remember that it is not unusual to transfer psychiatric patients from one 
hospital to another.	Episodes and spells	2n		Rules 130, 140 and 320	
1649	Episode start date check flag	epis_cfl	This field validates the episode start date (epistart).	Episodes and spells	1n		Not applicable (derived by rule 30)	
1650	Episode status	epistat	This field tells you whether the episode had finished before the end of the HES data-year (ie 
whether the episode was still 'live' at midnight on 31 March). 
For example, if a patient was admitted on 25 March 2005 and was not discharged (or 
transferred to the care of another consultant) until 4 April 2005, there will be a record 
describing the unfinished episode (episode status = 1) in the 2004-05 data, and a separate 
record describing the finished episode (episode status = 3) in the 2005-06 data. 
Because hospital providers are advised not to include clinical data (diagnosis and operation 
codes) in unfinished records, these are normally excluded from analyses. 
Also, if unfinished episodes are included in time series analyses - where data for more than 
one year is involved - there is a danger of counting the same episode twice.	Episodes and spells	1n		Rules 170 and 180	
1651	Episode type	epitype	This field contains a code that defines the type of episode, so that groups of similar episodes 
can be formed.	Episodes and spells	1n		Rules 150 & 160	
1652	Hospital provider spell number	provspno	Hospital provider spell number. A number to provide a unique identifier for each Hospital 
Provider Spell for a Health Care Provider.	Episodes and spells	12an	From 1997-98	None	
1653	Ward type at start of episode	wardstrt	This field contains a code that defines the characteristics of a ward. The code has six parts: 
AABCDEF.	Episodes and spells	7n	From 1997-98 until 31 March 2001	None	
1654	Cancer network	cannet	The cancer network that each postcode falls within. Further information on Cancer Network 
can be found on the Department of Health website 
[http://www.dh.gov.uk/en/Healthcare/NationalServiceFrameworks/Cancer/DH_4068463].	Geographical	3an	From 2008-09 onwards	Not applicable (derived from postcode)	
1655	Cancer registry	canreg	The cancer registry that each postcode falls within. Further information on Cancer Registries 
can be found on the Department of Health website 
[http://www.dh.gov.uk/en/Healthcare/NationalServiceFrameworks/Cancer/DH_4068586].	Geographical	5an	From 2008-09 onwards	Not applicable (derived from postcode)	
1656	Census Output Area, 2001	Oacode	Census Output Areas (OAs) are small geographical areas that cover similar population sizes, 
according to the 2001 census, and are as socially homogenous as possible. 
There are 165,665 Census Output Areas in England. The first six characters of this derived 
field represent the 2003 statistical ward. The Census output area, 2001 (oacode) field 
contains sensitive data. 
Access to it requires the approval of the Database Monitoring Sub-Group (DMSG).	Geographical	10an	From 2003-04 onwards	Data not cleaned	
1657	Census Output Area, 2001 (6 character)	oacode6	A derived field showing the six-character ward identifier contained in the Census Output Area 
data. 
The structure is CCDDWW.	Geographical	6an		Data not cleaned	
1658	County of residence	rescty	This field contains a code that defines the county of residence of the patient. It is derived from 
the patient's postcode in the field homeadd.	Geographical	2n		Not applicable (derived by rule 1200)	
1659	Current electoral ward	currward	This derived field contains a code which defines the current electoral ward of the patient. It is 
derived from the patient's postcode in the field homeadd. 
When this field is concatenated with the other local authority component, resladst, the result is 
a unique value.	Geographical	2a		Not applicable	
1660	Electoral ward in 1981	ward81	This field contains a code that indicates the patient's local authority and electoral ward of 
residence in 1981. It is derived from the patient's postcode in the field homeadd. From the 
1996-1997 data year, this field becomes ward91.	Geographical	5a		Not applicable (derived by rule 1200)	
1661	Electoral ward in 1991	ward91	This field contains the patient's full frozen 1991 Census electoral ward and local authority of 
residence. It is derived from the patient's postcode in the field homeadd.	Geographical	6a	1996-99 to 1998-99	Not applicable (derived by rule 1200)	
1662	Electoral ward in 1998	ward98	This field contains the patient's full frozen 1998 Census electoral ward and local authority of 
residence. It is derived from the patient's postcode in the field homeadd.	Geographical	6a	1999-00 to 2000-01	Not applicable (derived by rule 1200)	
1663	Government office region of residence	resgor	This derived field contains a code that defines the Government Office Region of residence of 
the patient. It is derived from the patient's postcode in the field homeadd.	Geographical	2an	1996-97 onwards	Not applicable (derived by rule 1200)	
1664	Government office region of treatment	gortreat	Goverment Office Region (GOR) of treatment. This field is derived from the hospital provider 
code (procode). It indicates the GOR area within which the treatment took place.	Geographical	1a	From 2002-03	Not applicable (derived by rule 1145)	
1665	Health authority of residence	resha	Health authority (HA) of residence (contains the district health authority of residence prior to 1 
April 1996). 
This derived field contains the code for the HA in which the patient lived immediately before 
admission. 
Resha is derived from the patient's postcode in the field homeadd. (This may not be the area 
where treatment took place (hatreat).) 
If homeadd is not recognised, resha may be derived from the health authority of residence 
notified by the hospital (har). 
From 2002-03 information relating to the strategic health authority of residence is available.	Geographical	3a		Not applicable - derived by the following rule: Rule 1200	
1666	Health authority of treatment	hatreat	This field indicates the health authority (HA) where the treatment took place. It is derived from 
the hospital provider code (procode). Health authority of treatment (contains the district health 
authority of treatment prior to 1 April 1996).	Geographical	3a		Not applicable (derived by rule 1145)	
1667	Local authority district	resladst	This derived field contains a code for the patient's county (first two characters) and local 
authority district (last two characters) of residence. It is derived from the patient's postcode in 
the field homeadd. 
This field is used in conjunction with currward (current electoral ward) to produce a unique 
value indicating the ward within a given district where the patient resided (ie because identical 
Currward codes are allocated to many local authority districts, currward is meaningless in 
isolation). 
If the patient is resident within a Unitary Authority, the first two characters will be 00 (zero, 
zero) and the local authority component may not be useable.	Geographical	4an		Not applicable (derived by rule 1200)	
1668	Local authority district in 1998	lad98	This derived field contains a code for the patient's county (first two characters) and local 
authority district (last two characters) of residence. It is derived from the patient's postcode 
(homeadd). 
This field is used in conjunction with currward (current electoral ward) to produce a unique 
value indicating the ward within a given district where the patient resided (ie because identical 
Currward codes are allocated to many local authority districts, currward is meaningless in 
isolation). 
If the patient is resident within a Unitary Authority, the first two characters will be 00 (zero, 
zero) and the local authority component may not be useable.	Geographical	4an	1999-00 to 2000-01	Not applicable (derived item)	
1669	Lower Super Output Area	soal	Lower Super Output Areas are aggregations of Output Areas. There are 32,482 Lower Super 
Output Areas in England. 
The first character is either E for England or W for Wales. 
The next two characters are 01 for Lower Super Output Area and the remaining six 
characters make up the unique 6-digit tag for each zone.	Geographical	10an		Data not cleaned	
1670	Middle Super Output Area	soam	Middle Super Output Areas are aggregations of Output Areas. 
The first character is either E for England or W for Wales. 
The next two characters are 02 for Middle Layer and the remaining six characters make up 
the unique 6-digit tag for each zone. There are 6,780 Middle Super Output Areas in England.	Geographical	10an		Data not cleaned	
1671	Ordnance Survey grid reference	gridlink	Ordnance survey postcode grid reference. Gridlink' is the name for a set of branded 
postcode products produced by the Gridlink Consortium (Royal Mail, Ordnance Survey (GB), 
General Register Office for Scotland (GROS), Ordnance Survey of Northern Ireland (OSNI) 
and ONS). 
The Gridlink field in HES is only available to the NHS.	Geographical	9n	From 2002-03 onwards	Not applicable (derived by rule 1200)	
1672	Patient's health authority of residence, provided by	NHS	The patient's health authority of residence provided by the NHS.	har	Geographical	3an	None	
1673	Patient's primary care trust of residence	respct	This derived field contains the code for the primary care trust (PCT) in which the patient lived 
immediately before admission. It is derived from the patient's postcode in the field homeadd.	Geographical	3an	From 1996-97	Not applicable (derived by rule 1200)	
1674	Patient's primary care trust of residence ' historic	respct02	This derived field contains the code for the primary care trust (PCT) in which the patient lived 
immediately before admission. It is derived from the patient's postcode in the field homeadd.	Geographical	naa or nan		Not applicable (derived by rule 1200)	
1675	Patient's primary care trust of residence ' current	respct06	This derived field contains the code for the primary care trust (PCT) in which the patient lived 
immediately before admission. It is derived from the patient's postcode in the field homeadd.	Geographical	3an		Not applicable (derived by rule 1200)	
1676	Patient's strategic health authority of residence	resstha	This derived field contains the code for the strategic health authority (SHA) in which the 
patient lived immediately before admission. It is derived from the patient's postcode in the 
field homeadd.	Geographical	3an	From 1996-97	Not applicable (derived by rule 1200)	
1677	Patient's strategic health authority of residence -	historic	This derived field contains the code for the strategic health authority (SHA) in which the 
patient lived immediately before admission. It is derived from the patient's postcode in the 
field homeadd.	resstha02	Geographical	3an	Not applicable (derived by rule 1200)	
1678	Patient's strategic health authority of residence -	current	This derived field contains the code for the strategic health authority (SHA) in which the 
patient lived immediately before admission. It is derived from the patient's postcode in the 
field homeadd.	resstha06	Geographical	3an	Not applicable (derived by rule 1200)	
1679	Primary care trust area of main provider	pcttreat	This field is derived from the hospital provider code (procode). It indicates the PCT area of 
the main provider of treatment. Note that the PCT itself may be the provider of treatment. 
Note: This field was formerly known as 'Primary care trust area of treatment'.	Geographical	3an	From 1996-97	Not applicable (derived by rule 1145)	
1680	Region of treatment	rotreat	Region of treatment (contains the Regional Health Authority of treatment prior to 1 April 
1996). This derived field is extracted from the hospital provider code (procode). 
It defines the Regional Office (RO) where the treatment took place.	Geographical	3an		Not applicable (derived by rule 1145)	
1681	Regional office of residence	resro	Regional office (RO) of residence (contains the regional health authority of residence prior to 
1 April 1996). 
It contains the code for the RO in which the patient lived immediately before admission. It is 
derived from the patient's postcode in the field homeadd.	Geographical	3an	From 1996-97	Not applicable - derived by the following rules: Rule 1200	
1682	Rural/Urban Indicator	rururb_ind	Describes the nature of an Output Area in terms of its morphology (hamlet, town, urban, etc) 
and context (sparse or less sparse).	Geographical	1n		Data not cleaned	
1683	Site code of treatment	sitetret	This field contains a code that defines the site on which the patient was treated within an 
organisation.	Geographical	5an	From 1997-98	None	
1684	Strategic health authority area of treatment	sthatret	This field is derived from the hospital provider code (procode). It indicates the strategic health 
authority (SHA) area within which the treatment took place.	Geographical	3an	From 1996-97	Not applicable (derived by rule 1145)	
1685	Super output area	soacode	Super Output Areas are aggregations of Output Areas. There are 3 types of Super Output 
Area, Lower Layer, Middle Layer, and Upper Layer. 
The first character is either E for England or W for Wales. 
The next two characters are either 01 for Lower Layer, or 02 for Middle Layer and the 
remaining six characters make up the unique 6-digit tag for each zone. There are 32,482 
Lower Layer Super Output Areas in England 
There are 6,780 Middle Layer Super Output Areas in England 
There are likely to be approximately 2,000 Upper Layer Super Output Areas in England. For 
more information about Super Output Areas see the National Statistics website.	Geographical	10an		Data not cleaned	
1686	Westminster parliamentary constituency	pcon	The Westminster Parliamentary Constituency code for each postcode. Pseudo codes are 
included for Channel Islands and Isle of Man. The field will be blank for postcodes with no grid 
reference.	Geographical	3n	From 2008-09 onwards	Not applicable (derived from postcode)	
1687	HRG version n.n (HES generated)	hrg_n.n	This HES derived field contains healthcare resource group (HRG) values. HES adds the two 
most recent versions of HRG codes to records. 
For example, a record for 2004-05 will have codes for HRG version 3.1 and HRG version 3.5.	Healthcare Resource Groups	3an		Not applicable	
1688	Trust derived dominant procedure	domproc	Contains the dominant procedure (operation) code assigned as part of the (NHS) HRG 
derivation process and submitted to SUS.	Healthcare Resource Groups	4an, - or &	2001-02 to 2008-09	Rule 570	
1689	Trust derived HRG value	hrgnhs	The Trust derived HRG value as submitted to SUS takes into account the dominant grouping 
procedure (domproc) and may differ from the HES derived HRG (HRG_n.n).	Healthcare Resource Groups	3an	2001-02 to 2008-09	Not applicable	
1690	SUS generated HRG	sushrg	The SUS PbR derived healthcare resource group (HRG) code (HRG4 from 2009-10) at 
Episode level.	Healthcare Resource Groups	5an	From 2009-10		
1691	SUS generated core spell HRG	suscorehrg	The SUS PbR derived healthcare resource group (HRG) code (HRG4 from 2009-10) at Spell 
level. 
Analysing this field by episode in HES could lead to over-counting.	Healthcare Resource Groups	5an	From 2009-10		
1692	SUS generated HRG version number	sushrgvers	The version number for the SUS generated HRG code (sushrg).	Healthcare Resource Groups	3an	From 2009-10	Not applicable	
1693	Version no. of Trust derived HRG	hrgnhsvn	The version number for the Trust derived HRG value (hrgnhs).	Healthcare Resource Groups	3an	2001-02 to 2008-09	Not applicable	
1694	Anaesthetic given during labour or delivery	delpren	This field contains a code which defines the anaesthetic or analgesic administered before and 
during labour and delivery.	Maternity	1n		Rule 730	
1695	Anaesthetic given post-labour or delivery	delposn	This field contains a code which defines the anaesthetic or analgesic administered after 
delivery.	Maternity	1n		Rule 730	
1696	Antenatal days of stay	antedur	This derived field contains the number of days between the start of the episode (epistart) and 
the date of delivery of the first baby (dobbaby).	Maternity	3n		Not applicable (derived by rule 800)	
1697	Baby sequence number	babyseq	Birth sequence.	Maternity	1n		None	
1698	Baby's age in days	neodur	This field contains the age in days of a baby admitted as a patient. It is derived from 
admission date (admidate) and date of birth (dob). If the baby is older than 27 days, neodur is 
not calculated.	Maternity	2n		Not applicable	
1699	Birth date (baby)	dobbaby	Baby's date of birth. This item appears for each baby on multiple birth delivery records. The 
Birth date - baby (dobbaby) field contains sensitive data. 
Access to it requires the approval of the Database Monitoring Sub-Group (DMSG).	Maternity	dd/mmyyyy (Date)		Rule 670	
1700	Birth order	birorder	The position in the sequence of births. This item appears for each baby on multiple birth 
delivery records. 
From 1996-97 the same value (1) is used for a single birth or the first born of several. Up until 
March 2002, only the first six births were recorded.	Maternity	1n or X		Rule 720	
1701	Birth weight	Birweit	This field contains the weight of the baby in grams immediately after birth. This item appears 
for each baby on multiple birth delivery records.	Maternity	4n		Rules 740 and 760	
1702	Delivery place change reason	delchang	This field contains a code that defines the reason for changing the delivery place type.	Maternity	1n		Rules 710 and 750	
1703	Delivery method	delmeth	This field contains a code which defines the method used to deliver a baby that is a 
registrable birth. 
The code is obtained from the ICD classification for delivery method. This item appears for 
each baby on multiple birth delivery records.	Maternity	1n or X		Rules 710 and 753	
1704	Delivery method derived	delmethd	A derived field providing delivery method from OPCS 3- or 4-character (where applicable) 
main operation codes.	Maternity	2n	From 2008-09 onwards	Not applicable (derived by rule 0765)	
1705	Delivery place (actual)	Delplace	This field contains a code which defines the actual type of delivery place (The intended 
delivery place is in delintn). 
This item appears for each baby on multiple birth delivery records.	Maternity	1n		Rules 710 and 753	
1706	Delivery place (intended)	delinten	This field contains a code which defines the intended type of delivery place. The initial 
intention is designated by the General Medical Practitioner (GMP) and midwife, or by the 
GMP and hospital staff. 
The decision is normally made when the mother is assessed for delivery. The actual delivery 
place type is in delplac.	Maternity	1n		Rules 710 and 750	
1707	First antenatal assessment date	anasdate	This field contains the date when a pregnant woman was first assessed and arrangements 
were made for antenatal care. 
This is not necessarily the date when delivery arrangements were made.	Maternity	dd/mm/yyyy (Date)		None	
1708	Gestation period in weeks at first antenatal assessment	anagest	Gestation period in weeks at the date of the first antenatal assessment. This field is calculated from anadate, gestat and the dobbaby.	Maternity	2nn		Not applicable (derived by rule 790)	
1709	Length of gestation	gestat	The fields contain the number of completed weeks of gestation according to the World Health 
Organization definition, which specifies time from the first day of the last menstrual period. If 
this date is not reliable, an estimate is provided. 
This item appears for each baby on multiple birth delivery records.	Maternity	2n		Rules 710 and 753	
1710	Birth status	birstat	This field contains a code which indicates whether the baby was born alive or dead (still birth). 
A still birth is a birth after a gestation period of 24 weeks (168) days where the baby shows no 
sign of life when delivered. 
This item appears for each baby on multiple birth delivery records.	Maternity	1n		Rules 710 and 753	
1711	Labour / delivery onset method	delonset	This field contains a code which defines the method used to induce (initiate) labour, rather 
than to accelerate it.	Maternity	1n		Rules 710 and 750	
1712	Mother's age at delivery	matage	This field contains the mother's age in whole years on the date of delivery. It is calculated 
from the mother's date of birth and the first baby's date of birth.	Maternity	3n		Not applicable (derived by rule 810)	
1713	Mother's date of birth	motdob	This field contains the mother's date of birth. It appears on birth records. The Mother's date of 
birth (motdob) field contains sensitive data. 
Access to it requires the approval of the Database Monitoring Sub-Group (DMSG).	Maternity	dd/mm/yyyy (Date)		Rule 690	
1714	Mother's data of birth check flag	motdob_cfl	Codes in this field validate the mother's date of birth (motdob).	Maternity	1n		Not applicable	
1715	Neonatel level of care	neocare	This field contains a code that defines the level of care given to a new born child. (Along with 
psychiatric patient status (admistat), this field replaces the V code indicator (vind).)	Maternity	1n	From 1996-97	Rules 360 and 370	
1716	Number of babies	numbaby	This field contains the number of babies delivered at the end of a single pregnancy. Both live 
and stillborn babies are counted. Until 2002-03, a maximum of 6 babies could be recorded in 
HES.	Maternity	1n or X		Rules 710 and 750	
1717	Number of baby tails	numtailb	This is the number of valid baby groups on the episode record. A valid baby group is defined 
as one which has a valid birthweight and a valid delivery method. This field defaults to 1.	Maternity	1n		Rule 770	
1718	Number of previous pregnancies	numpreg	This field contains the number of previous pregnancies that resulted in a registrable birth (live 
or still born). It appears on delivery records. 
In practice, numpreg1 has often been filled with the 'Not known' code, and the remainder 
have been left blank.	Maternity	2n		Rule 750	
1719	Postnatal stay	postdur	This derived field contains the number of days between the baby's birth and the end of the 
finished episode. It is calculated from episode end date (epiend) and the first baby's date of 
birth (dobbaby).	Maternity	3n		Not applicable (derived by rule 820)	
1720	Resuscitation method	biresus	This field contains a code that identifies the method used to get the baby breathing normally. 
This item appears for each baby on multiple birth delivery records.	Maternity	1n		Rules 710 and 753	
1721	Sex of baby	sexbaby	This field contains a code that defines the sex of the baby. This item appears for each baby 
on multiple birth delivery records.	Maternity	1n		None	
1722	Status of person conducting delivery	delstat	This field normally provides the status of the person conducting the delivery. When a student 
delivers the baby, the code of the supervisor should be given. 
This item appears for each baby on multiple birth delivery records.	Maternity	1n		Rules 710 and 753	
1723	Well baby flag	well_baby_ind	Codes in this field indicate whether the episode relates to a well baby (a neonate receiving 
normal levels of care, usually given by a mother or mother substitute). 
Note: This field was formerly known as 'Well Baby Check Flag'.	Maternity	1a	All years	Not applicable	
1724	Commissioner code	purcode	This field contains a code for the organisation commissioning the patient's treatment. There 
are six main types of purchaser, the prevalence of each being dependent on the data year.	Organisation	5an		Rule 340	
1725	Commissioner code status	purval	A derived field that indicates whether the purchaser code (purcode) is one that is recognised 
throughout the NHS. 
If not, the code may have been agreed locally between the hospital provider and the health 
care purchaser.	Organisation	1n	From 1995-96	Not applicable (derived by rule 1150)	
1726	Commissioner's regional office	purro	This field contains a code which identifies the Regional Office (RO) in which the purchaser is 
located. It is derived from the purcode field. 
The current codes include those used in 1995-96 and those used subsequently. There were 
alterations to the codes from April 1996 and April 1999 to reflect changes in the regional 
organisation.	Organisation	5an	From 1995-96 to 2001-02	Not applicable (derived by rule 1150)	
1727	Commissioner's strategic health authority	purstha	This field contains a code which identifies the strategic health authority (SHA) in which the 
commisioner is located. It is derived from the purcode field.	Organisation	3an	From 2002-03	Not applicable (derived by rule 1155)	
1728	Commissioning serial number	csnum	Contains the commissioning serial number (used in HES to identify OATs - out of area 
treatments). This is a number used to uniquely identify a NHS service agreement by an 
organisation acting as commissioner of patient care services.	Organisation	6an	From 2000-01	Data not cleaned	
1729	Health authority area where patient's GP was	registered	Provides the health authority area in which the patient's GP is registered.	gppracha	Organisation	3an	Not applicable (derived by rule 1110)	
1730	Primary care group	pcgcode	A derived field providing the primary care group responsible for the patient.	Organisation	5an	From 1999-00 to 2001-02	Not applicable (derived by rule 1160)	
1731	Primary care trust area where patient's GP was	registered	This field gives details of the primary care trust area in which the patient's GP is registered.	gpprpct	Organisation	3an	Not applicable (derived by rule 1125)	
1732	Primary care trust of responsibility	pctcode	A derived field providing the primary care trust responsible for the patient. Commissioning 
responsibility for individual patients rests with the primary care trust (PCT) with whom the 
patient is registered. 
This means that patients with a GP in one PCT area may reside in a neighbouring or other 
area but remain the responsibility of the PCT with whom their GP of registration is associated. 
PCTs are also responsible for non-registered patients who are resident within their 
boundaries.	Organisation	3an	From 1997-98 to 2005-06	Not applicable (derived by rule 1160)	
1733	Primary care trust of responsibility - historic	pctcode02	A derived field providing the primary care trust responsible for the patient. Commissioning 
responsibility for individual patients rests with the primary care trust (PCT) with whom the 
patient is registered. 
This means that patients with a GP in one PCT area may reside in a neighbouring or other 
area but remain the responsibility of the PCT with whom their GP of registration is associated. 
PCTs are also responsible for non-registered patients who are resident within their 
boundaries.	Organisation	3an	From 2006-07	Not applicable (derived by rule 1160)	
1734	Primary care trust of responsibility - current	pctcode06	A derived field providing the primary care trust responsible for the patient. Commissioning 
responsibility for individual patients rests with the primary care trust (PCT) with whom the 
patient is registered. 
This means that patients with a GP in one PCT area may reside in a neighbouring or other 
area but remain the responsibility of the PCT with whom their GP of registration is associated. 
PCTs are also responsible for non-registered patients who are resident within their 
boundaries.	Organisation	3an	From 2006-07	Not applicable (derived by rule 1160)	
1735	Provider code	procodet	This field gives a combination of 3-character and 5-character provider codes. 
Procodet enables you to view a combined list of codes, and related data, from: 
1. Primary care trusts (3 character, beginning with 5) 
2. NHS trusts (3 character, beginning with R. Trusts with associated treatment centres will 
have an '- X' following their code) 
3. NHS trust treatment centres (5 character 
listed separately to the NHS trusts) 
4. Independent providers (5 character, beginning with 8) 
5. Independent sector healthcare providers (5 character, beginning with N) 
For 3-character codes only see procode (provider code - 3 character) and for 5-character 
codes only see procode (provider code).	Organisation	5an			
1736	Provider code - 3 character	procode3	A provider code is a unique code that identifies an organisation acting as a health care 
provider. 
The code is managed by the National Administrative Codes Service (NACS) and supports the 
identification of organisations exchanging information within the NHS. 
Procode3 contains only the first three characters (the organisation code) and can be used to 
identify an individual provider (eg NHS Trust or PCT).	Organisation	3an			
1737	Provider code - 5 character	procode	A provider code is a unique code that identifies an organisation acting as a health care 
provider. 
The code is managed by the National Administrative Codes Service (NACS) and supports the 
identification of organisations exchanging information within the NHS. 
Procode contains the complete NHS provider code (ie organisation code plus site code).	Organisation	5an			
1738	Provider type	protype	Healthcare provider type.	Organisation	Various		Not applicable (derived from reference data)	
1739	Regional office area where patient's GP was registered	gppracro	Provides the Regional Office area in which the patient's GP is registered.	Organisation	3an	From 2002-03	Not applicable (derived by rule 1120)	
1740	Strategic health authority area where patient's GP was	registered	This field gives the stategic health authority (SHA) area in which the patient's GP is 
registered.	gpprstha	Organisation	3an	Not applicable (derived by rule 1125)	
1741	Administrative & legal status of patient	category	Many NHS hospitals have private wards where private patients may use the accommodation 
and services of the hospital provider. 
Some hospitals also provide amenity beds, usually located in small side wards for which a 
charge is made for the accommodation. 
Both of these categories of patient are defined by the NHS Act of 1977. Any categories of 
patient, whether NHS, private or amenity patients, can be formally detained under the 
provisions of the Mental Health Act 1983 and other legislation. 
Most patients in NHS hospitals or hospital units will come under category 10 (see below). 
* Codes 13, 23 and 33 were introduced at the start of the 1994-95 HES year (1 April 1995)	Patient	2n	Until 31 March 2002	Not applicable (derived by the Secondary Uses Service from 
Administrative category and Legal Status Classification)	
1742	Administrative category	admincat	Administrative category on admission.	Patient	2n	From 2000-01	Rule 125 (from 2002-03 onwards)	
1743	Admin category at start of episode	admincatst	The patient's administrative category at the start of each episode of care. 
This may change during a spell as the patient may, for example, opt to change from NHS to 
private health care.	Patient	2an	2007-08, Quarter 3 onwards	Data not cleaned	
1744	Admission episode flag	admiflag	-	Patient	1a		None	
1745	Age at activity date	activage	The patient's age, in years, at the time of activity, such as admission, discharge or birth.	Patient	3n	2007-08, Quarter 3 onwards	Data not cleaned	
1746	Age at end of episode	endage	This derived field contains the patient's age in whole years at the end of a finished episode 
(from 1 to 115 (1990-91 to 1994-95) and from 1 to 120 (1995-96 onwards). 
It is calculated from the episode end date (epiend) and the patient's date of birth (dob). 
This field is only provided for finished episodes (episode status - epistat - is 3) and for 
general, delivery or birth records (episode type - epitype - is 1, 2 or 3). 
For patients under one year old, special codes apply.	Patient	4n		Not applicable (derived by rule 280)	
1747	Age at start of episode	startage	This derived field, calculated from episode start date (epistart) and date of birth (dob), 
contains the patient's age in whole years (From 1 to 115 (1990-91 to 1994-95) and from 1 to 
120 (1995-96 onwards)). 
For patients under 1 year old, special codes in the range 7001 to 7007 apply.	Patient	4n		Not applicable (derived by rule 290)	
1748	Age on admission	Admiage	A patient's age, in years, at the date of admission.	Patient	3n	2007-08, Quarter 3 onwards	Data not cleaned	
1749	Age of baby in days	neodur	This field contains the age in days of a baby admitted as a patient. It is derived from 
admission date (admidate) and date of birth (dob). 
If the baby is older than 27 days, neodur is not calculated.	Patient	2n		Not applicable (derived by rule 300)	
1750	Date of birth - patient	dob	This field contains the patient's date of birth. For most enquiries the field startage (age at start 
of episode) is used. 
The Date or birth - patient (dob) field contains sensitive data. Access to it requires the 
approval of the Database Monitoring Sub-Group (DMSG).	Patient	dd/mm/yyyy (Date)		Rule 20	
1751	Date of birth check flag - patient	dob_cfl	Validation of patient's date of birth.	Patient	1n		Not applicable (derived by rule 20)	
1752	Discharge episode flag	disflag		Patient	1a		None	
1753	Ethnic category	ethnos	This field contains a code that specifies some ethnic groups and some nationalities. It was 
introduced from the 1995-96 data year. 
From April 2001 the codes were changed to conform to the 2001 census classification. 
However, HES continued to accept the old codes as well as the new codes for the 2001-02 
and 2002-03 data years. 
Ethnic Category has been mandatory for Admitted Patient Care Commissioning Dataset 
central returns since 1995. However birth episodes, and other CDS types have been 
optional. 
From April 2009 Ethnic Category will be mandatory for all CDS types. I.e. to include: birth 
episodes; unfinished birth episodes; other birth event types; Out Patient CDSs and Accident 
and Emergency CDSs. 
Note: 'Z ' not stated' means that the person had been asked and had declined either 
refusing to provide this information, or a genuine inablility to choose. 'X ' Not known' means 
that the person has not been asked or the patient was not in a condition to be asked. E.g. 
unconscious.	Patient	1n or X		Rule 10	
1754	Finished consultant episode flag	fceflag	-	Patient	1a		None	
1755	In year flag	inyrflag	-	Patient	1a		None	
1756	Legal category of patient	leglcat	The legal category of all formally and informally detained patients on admission. An informally 
detained patient is one who is not formally detained, but has been in hospital for a year or 
more in the care of a consultant in the psychiatric specialties. 
This item is required for all admissions to psychiatric specialties. The Legal category of 
patient (lelcat) field contains sensitive data. 
Access to it requires the approval of the Database Monitoring Sub-Group (DMSG).	Patient	2n	From 2000-01	None	
1757	Legal status classification code at start of episode	leglstatst	Required for all patients with a hospital provider spell that includes the care of a consultant in 
a psychiatric specialty or who have been discharged from such a spell and are receiving 
supervised aftercare under the provisions of the Mental Health Act 1995.	Patient	2an	2007-08, Quarter 3 onwards	Data not cleaned	
1758	Local patient identifier	lopatid	This field contains the number used to identify a patient within a health care provider. It may 
be different from the patient's case note number and may be assigned automatically by the 
hospital's patient administration system. 
The Local patient identifier (lopatid) field contains sensitive data. Access to it requires the 
approval of the Database Monitoring Sub-Group (DMSG).	Patient	10n	From 1997-98	None	
1759	NHS number	newnhsno	This field contains the NHS Number of the patient, which is the primary identifier of a person 
registered for health care it is unique. 
Records for babies under six weeks of age and for patients admitted through accident and 
emergency tend to have null entries for this field. The NHS Number (newnhsno) field contains 
sensitive data. 
Access to it requires the approval of the Database Monitoring Sub-Group (DMSG).	Patient	10n	From 1997-98	None	
1760	Patient ID - HES generated (original)	hesid_orig	Uniquely identifies a patient across all data years. It is generated by matching records for the 
same patient using a combination of NHS Number and local patient identifier, plus the 
patients' postcode, sex and date of birth.	Patient	10n	From 1997-98	Not applicable (derived data)	
1761	Patient identifier - HES generated	pseudo_hesid	This field uniquely identifies a patient across all data years. It is generated by matching 
records for the same patient using a combination of NHS Number, local patient identifier, 
postcode, sex and date of birth. 
Customers who request an extract will receive a unique version of the pseudo_hesid called 
the extract_hesid. 
Pseudo_hesid supercedes hesid.	Patient	32an		Not applicable	
1762	Postcode district of patient's residence	postdist	Contains the outward portion of the patient's postcode (ie all characters to the left of the 
space). 
The code ZZ99 indicates the postcode was either unavailable, or that the patient did not have 
one (eg because they were normally resident abroad).	Patient	4an		Not applicable (derived from homeadd by rule 1200)	
1763	Postcode of patient	homeadd	This field normally contains the patient's home postcode. However, if a patient is away from 
home for long periods, such as in a university hall of residence, the postcode of their typical 
residence is used instead. If the postcode contains fewer than eight characters, spaces are 
placed between the two parts of the postcode so that the second part always starts at the 
sixth character position. 
The Postcode of patient (homeadd) field contains sensitive data. Access to it requires the 
approval of the Database Monitoring Sub-Group (DMSG).	Patient	8an		Rule 330	
1764	Sex of patient	sex	This field contains a code which defines the sex of the patient.	Patient	1n		Rules 50, 60 and 650	
1765	Duration of elective wait	waitdays	The number of days that a patient waited from the date when a decision was taken for 
treatment to when they received the treatment.	Patient Pathway	4n	2007-08, Quarter 3 onwards	Not applicable: derived field	
1766	Earliest reasonable date offered	earldatoff	The earliest reasonable (as defined by hospital staff where a patient accepts an offer date the 
date is deemed reasonable) appointment or admission date offered. 
Where a patient cancels an appointment or offer for admission, the earliest reasonable offer 
date for the rearranged appointment/admission will remain as the earliest reasonable offer 
date of the cancelled appointment/admission. 
Where the healthcare provider cancels and rearrange an appointment/admission date, the 
earliest reasonable offer date for the re-arranged appointment/admission will be the date of 
the earliest reasonable offer made following cancellation.	Patient Pathway	dd/mm/yyyy (Date)	2007-08, Quarter 3 onwards	Data not cleaned	
1767	Organisation code (patient pathway ID issuer)	orgpppid	The organisation code of the patient pathway ID issuer. 
Where Choose and Book has been used, the Organisation Code for NHS Connecting For 
Health (X09) is used.	Patient Pathway	5an	2007-08, Quarter 3 onwards	Data not cleaned	
1768	Patient pathway ID	Patpathid	A code that, when combined with the organisation code of either the issuer or the 
organisation receiving the service request, identifies a patient's pathway. 
For example, the Unique Booking Reference Number of the first referral and X09 (the 
organisation code for NHS Connecting for Health).	Patient Pathway	20an	2007-08, Quarter 3 onwards	Data not cleaned	
1769	RTT period start date	rttperstart	The start date, for the referral to treatment period.	Patient Pathway	dd/mm/yyyy (Date)	From 2007-08, Quarter 3 onwards	Data not cleaned	
1770	RTT period status	rttperstat	The status of an activity, or anticipated activity, for the referral to treatment period.	Patient Pathway	2n	From 2007-08, Quarter 3 onwards	Data not cleaned	
1771	RTT period end date	rttperend	The end date, for the referral to treatment period.	Patient Pathway	dd/mm/yyyy (Date)	From 2007-08, Quarter 3 onwards	Data not cleaned	
1772	Unique booking reference number	bookrefno	The booking reference number assigned by the Connecting for Health Choose and Book 
System when a patient accepts an appointment date, regardless of whether they 
subsequently attend or cancel the appointment. Each booking reference number is unique.	Patient Pathway	12n	2007-08, Quarter 3 onwards	Data not cleaned	
1773	Admission date check flag	adm_cfl	Codes in this field indicate whether the patient's admission date is valid.	Period of care	1n	All years	Not applicable (derived by rule 35)	
1774	Date of admission	admidate	This field contains the date the patient was admitted to hospital at the start of a hospital spell. 
Admidate is recorded on all episodes within a spell.	Period of care	dd/mm/yyyy (Date)	All years	Rule 35	
1775	Date of decision to admit	elecdate	This field contains the date on which a consultant, or another member of the clinical staff, 
decided to admit the patient to a hospital. 
The patient may or may not be admitted immediately. The time between elecdate and 
admidate (admission date) is known as the waiting time.	Period of care	dd/mm/yyyy (Date)	All years	Rules 40 and 45	
1776	Date of decision to admit check flag	elec_cfl	Codes in this field indicate whether the decision to admit date is valid.	Period of care	1n	All years	Not applicable (derived by rules 40 and 45)	
1777	First regular day or night admission	firstreg	This field indicates whether the episode falls within a sequence of regular day and night 
admissions and, if so, whether it is the first or subsequent episode within the sequence.	Period of care	1n	From 2002-03	None	
1778	Method of admission	admimeth	This field contains a code which identifies how the patient was admitted to hospital. 
Admimeth is recorded on the first and also all subsequent episodes within the spell (ie where 
the spell is made up of more than one episode).	Period of care	2n	All years	Rules 65, 70 and 320	
1779	Source of admission	admisorc	This field contains a code which identifies where the patient was immediately prior to 
admission. 
Most patients are admitted from home, but there are some significant exceptions. 
In particular, this field differentiates between patients admitted from home and patients 
transferred from another hospital provider or institution.	Period of care	2n	All years	Rule 80	
1780	Waiting time	elecdur	This derived field contains the difference in days between the date on which it was decided to 
admit the patient (elecdate) and the actual admission date (admidate). 
Elecdur is only applicable where an elective admission (ie the admission method is 11, 12 or 
13) was scheduled and took place.	Period of care	4n		Not applicable (derived by rule 270)	
1781	Intended management	intmanig	This field contains a code that defines what was planned to happen. The patient classification 
(classpat) defines what actually happened.	Period of care	1n	From 1997-98	Rule 120	
1782	Main specialty	mainspef	This field contains a code that defines the specialty under which the consultant is contracted. 
It can be compared with tretspef, the specialty under which the consultant worked.	Period of care	3n or &		Rule 90 and 350	
1783	Patient classification	classpat	This field identifies day cases, ordinary admissions, regular day and regular night attenders, 
and the special case of mothers and babies using only delivery facilities. 
Data about regular day and regular night attenders are not available for analysis prior to 
2002-03. 
Since the introduction of the NHS wide clearing service in April 1996, this field has been 
derived from related items in the Commissioning Data Set (eg intended management).	Period of care	1n		Not applicable (derived by rule 260)	
1784	Treatment specialty	tretspef	This field contains a code that defines the specialty in which the consultant was working 
during the period of care. It can be compared with mainspef, the specialty under which the 
consultant is contracted. 
Prior to 1 April 1996, this data item contained the code for the sub-specialty (subspef). 
From April 2004 a new list of treatment specialities was introduced (see below). The new list 
describes the specialised service within which the patient was treated.	Period of care	3n or &		Rule 100	
1785	Date of discharge	disdate	This field contains the date on which the patient was discharged from hospital. 
It is only present in the record for the last episode of a spell.	Period of care	dd/mm/yyyy (Date)	All years	Rules 205, 210, 220 and 223	
1786	Destination on discharge	disdest	This field contains a code which identifies where the patient was due to go on leaving 
hospital. In most cases they return home. 
For many patients discharge destination is the same as source of admission (admisorc).	Period of care	2n		Rules 205, 210, 220 and 223	
1787	Discharge date check flag	dis_cfl	Codes in this field indicate whether the discharge date (disdate) is valid.	Period of care	1n		Not applicable (derived by rules 205, 210, 220 and 223)	
1788	Method of discharge	dismeth	This field contains a code which defines the circumstances under which a patient left hospital. 
For the majority of patients this is when they are discharged by the consultant. 
This field is only completed for the last episode in a spell.	Period of care	1n		Rules 205, 210, 220, 223 and 320	
1789	Bed days within the year	bedyear	This derived field provides the duration of an episode in days within the HES data year. It is 
derived from epistart (episode start date) and epiend (episode end date). 
For episodes that both start and finish in the data year, bedyear has the same value as epidur 
(episode duration). 
If the episode is unfinished, bedyear is calculated from epistart and the end of the data year. 
If epistart is before the beginning of the data year, bedyear is calculated from the start of the 
data year and epiend. 
If the record type is other maternity events (episode type 5 or 6), bedyear is null.	Period of care	3n	All years	Not applicable (derived by rule 240)	
1790	Beginning of spell	spelbgin	This derived field contains a code that defines whether the episode is the first of a spell and 
whether the spell started in the current or previous year. Other maternity events are excluded.	Period of care	1n		Not applicable (derived by rule 1170)	
1791	Date episode ended	epiend	This field contains the date on which a patient left the care of a particular consultant, for one 
of the following reasons: 
Discharged from hospital (includes transfers) or moved to the care of another consultant. 
A null entry either indicates that the episode was unfinished at the end of the data year, or the 
date was unknown.	Period of care	dd/mm/yyyy (Date)		Rules 190, 200 and 203	
1792	Date episode started	epistart	This field contains the date on which a patient was under the care of a particular consultant. If 
a patient has more than one episode in a spell, for each new episode there is a new value of 
epistart. 
However, the admission date which is copied to each new episode in a spell will remain 
unchanged and will be equal to the episode start date of the first episode in hospital.	Period of care	dd/mm/yyyy (Date)		Rule 30	
1793	Duration of spell	speldur	This derived field contains the difference in days between the admission date (admidate) and 
the discharge date (epiend) provided the discharge method (dismeth) confirms that the spell 
has finished. 
If the episode has not finished it is calculated from the end of the year and admidate.	Period of care	5n		Not applicable (derived by rule 1180)	
1794	End of spell	spelend	This field contains a code which defines whether the episode is the last of a spell. 
It is set for finished episodes (episode status - epistat - is 3) for general, delivery or birth 
episodes (episode type - epitype - is 1, 2 or 3) provided the discharge method (dismeth) 
confirms that the spell has finished.	Period of care	1a		Not applicable (derived by rule 1190)	
1795	Episode duration	epidur	This field contains the difference in days between the episode start date (epistart) and the 
episode end date (epiend). 
If the episode is unfinished epidur is set as null.	Period of care	5n		Not applicable (derived by rule 250)	
1796	Episode order	epiorder	This field contains the number of the episode within the current spell. 
All spells start with an episode where epiorder is 01. 
Many spells finish with this episode, but if the patient moves to the care of another consultant, 
a new episode begins. 
Episode numbers increase by 1 for each new episode until the patient is discharged (this 
includes transfers to another NHS trust or primary care trust - ie the first episode in the new 
trust will have epiorder 01). 
If the same patient returns for a different spell in hospital, epiorder is again set to 01. 
Admissions are calculated by counting the number of times epiorder is 01. 
When studying long term care, remember that it is not unusual to transfer psychiatric patients 
from one hospital to another.	Period of care	2n		Rules 130, 140 and 320	
1797	Episode start date check flag	epis_cfl	This field validates the episode start date (epistart).	Period of care	1n		Not applicable (derived by rule 30)	
1798	Episode status	epistat	This field tells you whether the episode had finished before the end of the HES data-year (ie 
whether the episode was still 'live' at midnight on 31 March). 
For example, if a patient was admitted on 25 March 2005 and was not discharged (or 
transferred to the care of another consultant) until 4 April 2005, there will be a record 
describing the unfinished episode (episode status = 1) in the 2004-05 data, and a separate 
record describing the finished episode (episode status = 3) in the 2005-06 data. 
Because hospital providers are advised not to include clinical data (diagnosis and operation 
codes) in unfinished records, these are normally excluded from analyses. 
Also, if unfinished episodes are included in time series analyses - where data for more than 
one year is involved - there is a danger of counting the same episode twice.	Period of care	1n		Rules 170 & 180	
1799	Episode type	epitype	This field contains a code that defines the type of episode, so that groups of similar episodes 
can be formed.	Period of care	1n		Rules 150 & 160	
1800	Hospital provider spell number	provspno	Hospital provider spell number. A number to provide a unique identifier for each Hospital 
Provider Spell for a health care provider.	Period of care	12an	From 1997-98	None	
1801	Ward type at start of episode	wardstrt	This field contains a code that defines the characteristics of a ward. The code has six parts: 
AABCDEF.	Period of care	7n	From 1997-98 until 31 March 2001	None	
1802	Code of GP practice	gpprac	Code of GP practice (registered GMP). This field was introduced for the 1997-98 data year. It 
contains a code which defines the practice of the patient's registered GP. It allows the GP to 
be notified about treatment given to the patient. 
The registered GP may not be the same as the referring GP.	Practitioner	6an	From 1997-98	Rule 440	
1803	Code of GP practice (pseudonymised)	pgpprac	A pseudonymised version of the code of a patient's registered GP practice (registered GMP). 
Please note that the registered GP may not be the same as the referring GP (see preferrer). 
The code of GP practice (gpprac) field contains the actual practice code.	Practitioner	16an			
1804	Code of patient’s registered or referring general medical practitioner	reggmp	This is normally the code of the general medical practitioner with whom the patient is registered.This field contains sensitive data. Access to it requires the approval of the Database Monitoring Sub-Group (DMSG).	Practitioner	8an	From 1997-98	Rule 430	
1805	Pseudonymised code of patient's registered or referring general medical practitioner	preggmp	A pseudonymised version of the code of the patient's registered or referring general medical practitioner. The Code of patient's registered or referring general medical practitioner (reggmp) field contains the actual codes. However, it is a sensitive field that requires the approval of the Database Monitoring Sub-Group before you can be given access to it.	Practitioner	16an			
1806	Consultant code	consult	The GMC code for the consultant, which identifies the consultant as an individual. Midwife 
and GP episodes are identified by a special code. 
The Consultant code (consult) field contains sensitive data. Access to it requires the approval 
of the Database Monitoring Sub-Group (DMSG).	Practitioner	8an	From 1997-98	Rules 420	
1807	Pseudonymised consultant team code	pconsult	A pseudonymised version of the General Medical Council (GMC) code for the consultant. The 
consultant code (consult) field contains the actual GMC code. 
However, it is a sensitive field that requires the approval of the Database Monitoring Sub-
Group before you can be given access to it.	Practitioner	16an			
1808	Referrer code	referrer	The code for the person referring the patient. This may be the GMC code for the consultant, 
or the code that defines the practice of the patient's registered GMP or GDP. 
This field contains sensitive data. Access to it requires the approval of the Database 
Monitoring Sub-Group (DMSG).	Practitioner	8an	From 1997-98	Rule 410	
1809	Pseudonymised referrer code	preferrer	A pseudonymised version of the code of the person referring the patient. The person referring 
patient (referrer) field contains the actual codes. 
However, it is a sensitive field that requires the approval of the Database Monitoring Sub-
Group before you can be given access to it.	Practitioner	16an			
1810	Referring organisation code	referorg	The organisation code of the organisation from which the referral is made, such as GP 
practice or NHS trust. 
The referring organisation code (referorg) field contains sensitive data. Access to it requires 
the approval of the Database Monitoring Sub-Group (DMSG).	Practitioner	6an	From 2002-03	None	
1811	Age at psychiatric census date	censage	This field is calculated from date of birth (dob) and the date of the psychiatric census (31 
March every year). 
It is only calculated for psychiatric census records 
if the episode type is not for a formally detained patient (epitype is not 4) or one that was 
admitted more than one year previously, censage is null. The maximum permitted value is 
120 years.	Psychiatric	3n		Not applicable (derived by rule 880)	
1812	Carer support indicator	carersi	This field contains a code which states whether carer support is available to the patient at 
home or other normal residence. 
This does not include any paid support or support from a voluntary organisation unless the 
patient is normally resident in a nursing home, group home or residential care home.	Psychiatric	2n	From 1997-98	Rule 400	
1813	Date detention commenced	detndate	For patients under a detention order at the date of the census, this field contains the date at 
which the first order commenced in the current continuous period of detention. 
Where the detention order is held by a hospital other than where the patient is at the date of 
the census, the latter is responsible for obtaining information relating to the detention order, 
and submitting the data.	Psychiatric	dd/mm/yyyy (Date)		Rule 110	
1814	Date detention commenced check flag	det_cfl	Validation of date detention commenced.	Psychiatric	1n		Not applicable (derived by rule 110)	
1815	Detention category	detncat	Indicates the legislation under which the patient was detained. 
The detention category (detncat) field contains sensitive data. Access to it requires the 
approval of the Database Monitoring Sub-Group (DMSG).	Psychiatric	1n	From 1999-00	Not applicable	
1816	Duration of care to psychiatric census date	cendur	Duration of care in days to the psychiatric census date. 
This field is calculated from admidate (admission date) and the date of the psychiatric census 
(31 March every year). The maximum permitted value is 29,200 days (approximately 80 
years).	Psychiatric	5n		Not applicable (derived by rule 870)	
1817	Duration of detention	detdur	This derived field contains the number of days between the date the current detention 
commenced (detndate) and the date of the psychiatric census (31 March of cendate). 
The maximum period is 29,200 days (approximately 80 years).	Psychiatric	5n		Not applicable (derived by rule 890)	
1818	Legal group of patient	legalgpa	This field contains a code that allocates the legal status of a patient to one of eight groups. 
(An aggregation of legal status of a patient on admission, leglcat.) 
The legal group of patient (legalgpa) field contains sensitive data. Access to it requires the 
approval of the Database Monitoring Sub-Group (DMSG).	Psychiatric	1n	From 2002-03	Not applicable (derived by rule 1135)	
1819	Legal group of patient (psychiatric)	legalgpc	Legal group of patient, an aggregation of legal status of a patient on psychiatric census date, 
leglstat. 
This field contains a code that allocates the legal status of a patient to one of eight groups. 
This field contains sensitive data. Access to it requires the approval of the Database 
Monitoring Sub-Group (DMSG).	Psychiatric	1n	From 2002-03	Not applicable (derived by rule 895)	
1820	Legal status classification	leglstat	This field contains a code which defines the legal status of all formally and informally detained 
patients at the date of the census. 
An informally detained patient is one who is not formally detained, but has been in hospital for 
a year or more in the care of a consultant in the psychiatric specialties. It is only for unfinished 
records of of episode type 4. 
 The Legal status classification (leglstat) field contains sensitive data. Access to it requires the 
approval of the Database Monitoring Sub-Group (DMSG).	Psychiatric	2n		None	
1821	Marital status (psychiatric)	marstat	This field contains a code that defines a patient's marital status where the consultant's 
specialty (mainspef) is one of the psychiatric specialties. 
Although the numerical codes were retired on 1/10/2006, these are still flowing so both sets of 
codes are seen.	Psychiatric	1an		Rule 355	
1822	Mental category	mentcat	This field contains a code which defines the mental categories of a patient in accordance with 
the designations in the Mental Health Act 1983. 
A patient should be included in only one mental category. If a patient has been assigned to 
more than one mental category, mental illness takes precedence over the others, and mental 
impairment or severe mental impairment takes precedence over psychopathic disorder.	Psychiatric	1n		None	
1823	Psychiatric history on admission	admistat	This field contains a code which identifies previous psychiatric care for psychiatric patients. 
It applies only to patients admitted or transferred to a consultant in one of the psychiatric 
specialties during a spell in hospital. It is recorded for the first such consultant episode but not 
for subsequent psychiatric consultant episodes or any non-psychiatric episodes. 
This field is used to indicate the turnover for psychiatric patients, and identify first time 
psychiatric admissions and re-admissions. Where a patient has a history of admission to 
several hospital providers, priority is given to the current hospital provider (code 1), regardless 
of whether the preceding admission was to the same hospital provider. 
This field replaces special (UK NHS specific) diagnosis codes commencing U69 (1 April 1989 
to 31 March 1995) and U51 (1 April 1995 to 31 march 1996), and also the HES derived V 
code indicator data item.	Psychiatric	1n	From 1996-97	Rule 380	
1824	Status of patient included in psychiatric census	censtat	This field contains a code which defines the legal status of the patient. It is derived from legal 
status (leglstat) and the length of stay recorded for the current spell.	Psychiatric	1n		Not applicable	
1825	V code indicator	vind	This derived field contains a code that indicates whether any of the diagnosis fields (diag_01 
to diag_07) contains a valid V code (see diag_nn). 
For 1995-1996 only, U codes replaced the V codes. Although classed as psychiatric data, 
values 1 to 3 indicate the level of neonatal care for a patient aged under 29 days. 
From 1996-97 this field was replaced by neocare and admistat.	Psychiatric	1n		Not applicable	
1826	Ward type at psychiatric census date	cenward	This field contains a code which defines the characteristics of a ward. The code has six parts: 
AABCDEF.	Psychiatric	7n		None	
1827	IMD Barriers to Housing and Service Domain	imd04hs	The Index of Multiple Deprivation (IMD) is a measure of multiple deprivation at Super Output 
Area level. 
The IMD has seven domains, one of which is the Barriers to Housing and Services Domain. 
The purpose of the Barriers to Housing and Services domain is to measure barriers to 
housing and key local services. This version of the Index was first published in 2004. 
See The English Indices of Deprivation 2004: Summary (revised) report 
[http://www.communities.gov.uk/documents/communities/pdf/131206.pdf] for further details.	Socio-economic	4n			
1828	IMD Crime Domain	imd04c	The Index of Multiple Deprivation (IMD) is a measure of multiple deprivation at Super Output 
Area level. 
The IMD has seven domains, one of which is the Crime Domain. The purpose of the Crime 
domain is to measure the incidence of recorded crime for four major crime themes: 
1. burglary 
2. theft 
3. criminal damage 
4. violence 
This version of the Index was first published in 2004. 
See The English Indices of Deprivation 2004: Summary (revised) report 
[http://www.communities.gov.uk/documents/communities/pdf/131206.pdf] for further details.	Socio-economic	3n			
1829	IMD Decile Group	imd04_decile	This field uses the IMD Overall Ranking to identify which one of ten groups a Super Output 
Area belongs to, from most deprived through to least deprived. 
This IMD version was first published in 2004. 
See The English Indices of Deprivation 2004: Summary (revised) report 
[http://www.communities.gov.uk/documents/communities/pdf/131206.pdf] for further details.	Socio-economic	20an			
1830	IMD Education Training and Skills Domain	imd04ed	The Index of Multiple Deprivation (IMD) is a measure of multiple deprivation at Super Output 
Area level. 
The IMD has seven domains, one of which is the Education, Skills and training Domain. The 
purpose of the Education, Skills and training domain is to capture the extent of deprivation in 
terms of education, skills and training in a local area. 
This version of the Index was first published in 2004. 
See The English Indices of Deprivation 2004: Summary (revised) report 
[http://www.communities.gov.uk/documents/communities/pdf/131206.pdf] for further details.	Socio-economic	4n			
1831	IMD Employment Deprivation Domain	imd04em	The Index of Multiple Deprivation (IMD) is a measure of multiple deprivation at Super Output 
Area level. 
The IMD has seven domains, one of which is the Employment Deprivation Domain. 
This domain measures employment deprivation conceptualised as involuntary exclusion of 
the working age population from the world of work. 
This version of the Index was first published in 2004. 
See The English Indices of Deprivation 2004: Summary (revised) report 
[http://www.communities.gov.uk/documents/communities/pdf/131206.pdf] for further details.	Socio-economic	3n			
1832	IMD Health and Disability Domain	imd04hd	The Index of Multiple Deprivation (IMD) is a measure of multiple deprivation at Super Output 
Area level. 
The IMD has seven domains, one of which is the Health Deprivation and Disability Domain. 
The purpose of the Health deprivation and disability domain is to identify areas with relatively 
high rates of: 
1. premature deaths 
2. impaired quality of life, due to poor health 
3. people with disabilities 
This version of the Index was first published in 2004. 
See The English Indices of Deprivation 2004: Summary (revised) report 
[http://www.communities.gov.uk/documents/communities/pdf/131206.pdf] for further details.	Socio-economic	3n			
1833	IMD Income Affecting Children Domain	imd04ic	The Index of Multiple Deprivation (IMD) is a measure of multiple deprivation at Super Output 
Area level. 
The IMD has seven domains, one of which is the Income Deprivation Domain. The Income 
Deprivation Affecting Children Index is a sub-set of the Income Deprivation Domain. 
The Index contains the percentage of a Super Output Area's children under 16 who were 
living in families receiving specific financial support, such as Income Support or Job Seeker's 
Allowance. 
This version of the Index was first published in 2004. 
See The English Indices of Deprivation 2004: Summary (revised) report 
[http://www.communities.gov.uk/documents/communities/pdf/131206.pdf] for further details.	Socio-economic	3n			
1834	IMD Income Affecting Adults Domain	imd04ia	The Index of Multiple Deprivation (IMD) is a measure of multiple deprivation at Super Output 
Area level. 
The IMD has seven domains, one of which is the Income Deprivation Domain. The Income 
Deprivation Affecting Older People Index is a sub-set of the Income Deprivation Domain. The 
Index contains the percentage of a Super Output Area's population aged 60 and over who are 
claiming Income Support or Job Seeker's Allowance. 
This version of the Index was first published in 2004. 
See The English Indices of Deprivation 2004: Summary (revised) report 
[http://www.communities.gov.uk/documents/communities/pdf/131206.pdf] for further details.	Socio-economic	3n			
1835	IMD Income Domain	imd04i	The Index of Multiple Deprivation (IMD) is a measure of multiple deprivation at Super Output 
Area level. 
The IMD has seven domains, one of which is the Income Deprivation Domain. The purpose of 
this Domain is to capture the proportions of the population experiencing income deprivation in 
an area. 
This version of the Index was first published in 2004. 
See The English Indices of Deprivation 2004: Summary (revised) report 
[http://www.communities.gov.uk/documents/communities/pdf/131206.pdf] for further details.	Socio-economic	3n			
1836	IMD Living Environment Domain	imd04le	The Index of Multiple Deprivation (IMD) is a measure of multiple deprivation at Super Output 
Area level. 
The IMD has seven domains, one of which is the Living Environment domain. The Living 
Environment domain focuses on deprivation with respect to the characteristics of the living 
environment. 
This version of the Index was first published in 2004. 
See The English Indices of Deprivation 2004: Summary (revised) report 
[http://www.communities.gov.uk/documents/communities/pdf/131206.pdf] for further details.	Socio-economic	4n			
1837	IMD Overall Rank	imd04rk	The IMD overall ranking is made by combining the seven IMD Domain scores using the 
following weights: 
- Income (22.5%) 
- Employment (22.5%) 
- Health Deprivation and Disability (13.5%) 
- Education, Skills and Training (13.5%) 
- Barriers to Housing and Services (9.3%) 
- Crime (9.3%) 
- Living Environment (9.3%) 
The SOA (Super Output Area) with a rank of 1 is the most deprived, and 32482 the least 
deprived, on this overall measure. 
This IMD version was first published in 2004. 
See The English Indices of Deprivation 2004: Summary (revised) report 
[http://www.communities.gov.uk/documents/communities/pdf/131206.pdf] for further details.	Socio-economic	5n			
1838	CDS extract date	cdsextdate	CDS extract date.	System	dd/mm/yyyy (Date)	2007-08, Quarter 3 onwards	Data not cleaned	
1839	CDS version number	cdsversion	The version of the commissioning data set (CDS) being used.	System	6an	2007-08, Quarter 3 onwards	Data not cleaned	
1840	CDS protocol identifier	cdsverprotid	CDS Protocol ID.	System	3an	2007-08, Quarter 3 onwards	Data not cleaned	
1841	CDS unique identifier	cdsuniqueid	CDS unique identifier.	System	35an	2007-08, Quarter 3 onwards	Data not cleaned	
1842	Combined grossing factor	gross_b	This field contains a value, calculated to four decimal places, that combines administrative 
(coverage) grossing (the value contained in data item gross_a) and clinical grossing. Clinical 
grossing compensates for the under counting of diagnoses or operations that occurs where 
cases contain a not known diagnosis code. 
The diagnostic data in a predefined group is analysed to ascertain the proportion of records 
that do not have a valid primary diagnosis. This shortfall in diagnostic coding is used to 
calculate a compensating factor. 
The clinical factor is multiplied by the value in gross_a to produce the combined grossing 
factor, gross_b. The default value for this field is 1.0000. It is overwritten when clinical 
grossing is selected.	System	7n		Not applicable	
1843	Coverage grossing factor	gross_a	This field contains a value that compensates for missing or additional HES records. 
The number of finished HES records in a predefined group are compared with the number for 
the same group reported from another source (currently the HES Activity Count). 
The ratio between the two provides a correction factor that can be applied to HES data. The 
default value for this field is 1.0000.	System	7n		Not applicable	
1844	Date data received	subdate	Date on which the data used to generate the HES record was received by the Secondary 
Uses Service (or the NHS-Wide Clearing Service (NWCS) prior to December 2006).	System	dd/mm/yyyy (Date)	From 2000-01	Data not cleaned	
1845	Ethnic category (audit version)	ethrawl	Ethnic category is supplied by the trusts as a two-character field. The left-hand character 
should contain the national code. A copy of the raw data found in the left hand character is 
held in ethraw.	System	1an		None	
1846	Ethnic character (audit version)	ethraw	Ethnic character is supplied by the trusts as a two-character field. Ethraw contains the left-
hand character. 
The right hand character being available for local use. A copy of the raw data found in the 
right hand character is held in ethrawl.	System	1a		None	
1847	NHS number status indicator	nhsnoind	Codes in this field indicate whether the patients' NHS Number is present, and if it is verified. If 
the NHS Number is absent, the indicator gives the reason why.	System	2n	From 2002-03	None	
1848	Origin of primary care group	pcgorig	This derived field indicates the basis on which the primary care group (PCG) code was 
assigned.	System	1n	From 1999-00 to 2005-06	Not applicable (derived by rule 1160)	
1849	Origin of primary care trust of responsibility	pctorig	This derived field indicates the basis on which the primary care trust (PCT) of responsibility 
code was assigned.	System	1n	From 1997-98 to 2005-06	Not applicable (derived by rule 1160)	
1850	Origin of primary care trust of responsibility - historic	pctorig02	This derived field indicates the basis on which the primary care trust (PCT) of responsibility 
code was assigned.	System	1n	From 2006-07	Not applicable	
1851	Origin of primary care trust of responsibility - current	pctorig06	This derived field indicates the basis on which the primary care trust (PCT) of responsibility 
code was assigned.	System	1n	From 2006-07	Not applicable	
1852	Patient identifier (HES generated) - basis of match	matchid	This field indicates the basis on which the HES ID was allocated.	System	1n	From 1997-98	Not applicable	
1853	Record identifier	epikey	This is a record identifier that is created by the HES system. The eight digits store a decimal 
number.	System	8n		Not applicable	
1854	SUS loaded staging date	suslddate	The date that the data was loaded into the SUS staging system.	System	dd/mm/yyyy (Date)	2007-08, Quarter 3 onwards	Data not cleaned	
1855	SUS record id	susrecid	SUS generated record identifier.	System	14n	2007-08, Quarter 3 onwards	Data not cleaned	
1856	SUS generated Spell ID	susspellid	SUS generated Spell ID	System	10n	From 2009-10	Data not cleaned	
